大丈夫
Are you all right?
一体何が
What happened?
It looks like the Aldnoah drive shut down.
アルドノアドライブが停止したようです
That shouldn't be possible!
そんなはずはありません　この船のアルドノアは姫様が起動したのです
This ship's Aldnoah was activated by Her Highness!
So long as she lives, it can't be shut down by another without her consent!
姫様が生きている限り　他人が勝手に止める事など出来ません
So long as she lives...
生きている限り…
Where is Seylum?!
セラムさんは
Where is she? Where is Seylum?!
どこだ　セラムさんは
Your selfless dream
君が見る夢は　古いインクで紙に書いた祈りのよう
is like a prayer written on paper with old ink
Your fragile hands seek support,
小さなその手が　縋るものも　今はまだ何処にも無い
and yet have nothing at all to cling to
それでも君の行く道を
But even so, I want to guard
the path you walk
奇麗なものは奇麗なままで　守り続けたいと思うよ
in all my beauty
空と水が星を染めて
I can see our skies and seas in the stars,
before they fall to make a rainbow
淡く虹を描いて散って
Light tears through the night and you sing
眩しい夜　君が歌う
How far will your voice travel?
声は何処まで届くのだろう
憧れの住まう蒼い星のひかり
This is the light of the blue planet I admire,
the light that we love helplessly
ただ僕らは恋をして
We sacrifice all we have at our disposal
たったひとつの未来の為に
for the only future we have left
今の全て奏でてみる
Let us fly
飛び立つよ　まだ暗い空へ
into the blackened sky
Damage?
被害は
Negligible damage to the hull. Departmental damage checks underway.
船体の損傷は軽微　各部所の被害は確認中
We are currently operating on auxiliary power.
現在　補助動力で稼働中です
It's a good thing we were flying at low altitude.
低空飛行が幸いしました
Our gravity field churned up the snow, so it was like a shock absorber.
重力場で砕かれた雪原が緩衝材になったみたいです
Launch our Cats and put them on watch.
艦載機を発進　警戒に当たれ
Repair any damaged areas ASAP.
被害のあった箇所は即刻修理
Engine room, inspect the Aldnoah drive and determine cause of shutdown.
機械室は　アルドノアドライブを点検　停止した原因を調査
Where is Capt. Magbaredge?
マグバレッジ艦長は
Bridge.
ブリッジ
至急メディックを寄越してください
Send medics immediately!
Captain? Where are you?
艦長　どちらに
Breathing and pulse are non-existent.
呼吸　心拍　共に停止
姫様
Princess!
Bring towels!
タオルを
除細動器を使う　水を拭かないと　早く
I'm going to use a defibrillator. We have to dry her off!
Hurry!
Right!
はい
I'll help.
手伝おう
カウンターショック200J　セット
Setting counter shock to 200 joules.
Clear.
離れて
I'll do it!
私がやります
駄目だ　体重が軽い
No, you're too light.
You think fast on your feet.
手際が良いですね
学校で習います
We learn this in school.
Students never take it seriously. All they do is giggle about the mouth-to-mouth.
学生は真面目に習いません　人工呼吸を冷やかすだけ
It could save a life.
命が懸かってます
Should I take over?
代わりましょうか
大丈夫です
I can handle it.
Milady!
姫様
Good.
良かった
大丈夫ですか
Are you all right?
伊奈帆さん　私は…
Inaho...
Where am I?
It looks like you passed out while
taking a shower. What happened?
シャワーを浴びて倒れたみたいです　どうしたんですか
I...
私は…
私は　彼女に…
I was attacked... by her!
動かないで
Don't move.
You...
あなた…
Rayet?
ライエさん　どうして
Why?
Where's the patient?!
患者は
Stay back!
来ないで
Get back! Get out of the room!
下がって　部屋の外に出て　早く
Now!
Dr. Yagarai.
耶賀頼先生
Yeah...
Who are you?
君は　何者だ
A Versian.
ヴァース　いいえ　火星人よ
No, a Martian.
Why?
どうして
The one who tried to assassinate you at the Shinawara parade
新芦原のパレードで　あなたを暗殺しようとしたのは　私の父
was my father.
He was a Martian spy living on Earth.
父は　地球に住む火星のスパイ
He was promised a title and a reward if he killed you.
あなたを殺せば　地位と報酬が約束されていた
But when he completed his mission, he was put down like a dog.
でも任務を終えると　無残に殺された　口封じの為に
To silence him!
Martians can't be trusted! Martians are all the enemy!
火星人なんて信用出来ない　火星人は皆敵
I can't go back to being a Martian.
私はもう　火星人には戻れない　でも　地球人でもない
But I'm not a Terran, either.
But you... you revealed yourself as a Martian!
なのに　あなたは火星人だって明かした
火星人なのに受け入れられて
In spite of that, you were accepted!
In spite of that, you made a place for yourself!
火星人なのに居場所が出来て
In spite of what you are!
火星人なのに…
I thought we were on the same side, but...
仲間だと思ってたのに
It's all your fault...
全部あなたのせい
My father is dead because you came here.
あなたが来たからお父様が死んだ
This war started because you came here.
あなたが来たから戦争が始まった
We were betrayed because you came here.
あなたが来たから裏切られた
I'm all alone because you came here.
あなたが来たから一人になった
Because you came... Because you came...
あなたが来たから　あなたが来たから　あなたが来たから
Because you came!
In spite of all that, how can they not hate you?!
なのに　なのに　どうしてあなたは…
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい　私が　あなたを不幸にしてしまったのですね
I've brought you...
nothing but misery, haven't I?
I was a fool.
私が　愚かだったのです
Milady!
姫様
I thought I was working towards peace.
平和を願ったつもりでした
I thought I was doing the right thing.
正しい事をしたつもりでした
でも　私がわがままを通したに過ぎませんでした
But I was merely acting like a spoiled child.
Relations with Earth are worse than ever because of me.
むしろ　地球との関係は悪くなってしまった
Many people have lost their lives.
たくさんの人が死にました
No matter how much I tell myself that I did nothing wrong,
どんなに間違った事はしていないと思い込んでも
現実には　大勢の人に　不幸が　降り掛かって
the reality of it is that I have brought misery to countless people's lives.
To yours. To your father's.
あなたにも　あなたのお父様にも　許して欲しいとは言いません
I will not ask you to forgive me.
でも　ごめんなさい
Nevertheless... I am sorry.
Why?
どうして　どうしてあなたが泣くの
Why are you crying?
My father tried to kill you!
お父様はあなたを殺そうとしたのよ
I tried to kill you, too!
私もあなたを殺そうとしてるのよ
Why won't you hate me?!
どうして憎まないの　どうして許すの
Why are you forgiving me?!
どうして優しくするの
Why are you being kind to me?
どうして　どうして　どうして
Why?! Why?! Why?!
Why?!
どうして
How stupid are you?
馬鹿じゃないの　もう　やめてよ
Give it a rest, already...
What am I even doing?
何やってんだろ　私
No!
駄目
What are you doing?!
何をするの
Automatics won't fire with the slide open.
オートマチックは　スライドが開くと撃発しない
I thought this was the best way to stop you without it discharging accidentally.
暴発させずに止めるには　こうするのがいいと思った
No, I meant to—
あなた
君が火星人か地球人かは　正直どうでもいい
To be honest, I couldn't care less if you're a Terran or a Martian.
You hate our enemies, and those enemies are trying to kill you.
君は僕らの敵を憎んでいるし　敵からも狙われている
そして何より　僕らと一緒に戦ってきた
But most importantly, you've fought at our side.
What other reasons do I need?
他にもまだ　理由がいる
You trust me?
私を信じるの
At the very least, I don't think we're enemies.
少なくとも僕達は敵じゃないはずだ
As to whether we'll be allies... that's up to you.
味方になるかは　君次第だけど
You might come to regret this.
後悔するかもよ
I'm taking you into custody. Warrant Officer Kaizuka.
あなたの身柄を拘束します
界塚准尉
はい
Yes, ma'am.
Do whatever you want.
好きにして
What's that? A Martian trinket?
それは　火星の工芸品ですか
No, I'm told that it's a Terran good luck charm.
いえ　地球のお守りだそうです
Dr. Yagarai, what's the princess' condition?
耶賀頼先生　姫殿下の容態は
She seems fine. But to be safe, she should rest for a while.
異常はありません
でも大事を取ってしばらく安静にした方が良いですね
I see. But I'm afraid that's out of the question.
そうですか　でもそうも言ってはいられません
I am fine. I shall see to the drive...
大丈夫です　すぐに…
Milady...
姫様
That reminds me, Captain.
そうだ　艦長
This is technically confidential information, but here.
本当は守秘義務があるんですけどね
What is it?
これは
A patient file. Lt. Marito's.
カルテです　鞠戸大尉の
Patient file?
カルテ
It's also a prescription. For you.
そして処方箋でもあります　艦長の
For me?
私の
Thanks.
ありがと
Compared to where I've been sleeping until now, this is paradise.
こんな所　今までに比べたら　天国みたい
Aldnoah drive online.
アルドノアドライブ　起動
We have power! We're good to go.
動力来ました　行けます
Deucalion, lift off.
デューカリオン　発進
That girl's father tried to kill the princess, a fellow Martian.
あの子の父親は　自分と同じ火星人であるお姫様を暗殺しようとした
Martians killed her father,
火星人の連中はあの子の父親を殺し
and then that Rayet girl turned a gun on the princess even though she's a Martian, too.
あのライエって子も火星人なのにお姫様に銃を向けた
そして　俺もこの手で親友を撃った
And I... killed my own best friend.
What was it like to be shot by a friend, Humeray?
味方に撃たれるのってどんな気分なんだろうな　ヒュームレイ
Slaine.
スレイン
This is our data on Tanegashima,
the island where you were retrieved.
そなたが回収された　種子島からのデータだ
巨大なドックと　造船設備
An enormous dock and shipbuilding facilities...
You saw a ship?
船を見たな
はい
Yes.
それはアルドノアを持つ船だな
And that ship was Aldnoah-equipped?
おそらくは
Most likely.
And was it Princess Asseylum who activated that Aldnoah?
そのアルドノアを起動したのは　アセイラム姫殿下か
You hold your tongue out of concern for her?
姫殿下の身を案じて黙するか
Are you familiar with this?
これを知っているか
What is it?
これは
デューカリオン
The Deucalion.
A Cataphract belonging to Viscountess Orlane that has gravity control capability.
重力制御能力を持つ　オルレイン子爵のカタフラクトだ
Viscountess Orlane?
オルレイン子爵
The woman who was to be my wife.
我が妻となる女性であった
We did our very utmost.
我らは尽力した
Using the power of the Aldnoah that His Majesty bestowed upon us, we ruled the people,
皇帝陛下から賜ったアルドノアの力を使い民を統べ
cultivated the wastelands of Vers, expanded our domain, and tried to amass wealth.
ヴァースの荒れた地を開拓し　領地を広げ　富を築こうとした
But no matter what we did, we would always be limited by something.
しかし　何をしようと　我らには限界があった
Limited?
限界
By water and air.
水と空気だ
In the time of the people of the ancient civilization that created Aldnoah,
アルドノアを生んだ古代文明人の時代は　まだ水と空気が豊富であった
water and air were yet plentiful.
But all Vers has now is an atmosphere that is nearly a vacuum
しかし今のヴァースは真空に近い薄い大気と
and what little water remains underground.
地下に残った僅かな水のみ
In fact, owing to that thin atmosphere, Vers is constantly buffeted by storms.
むしろ　薄い大気のせいで　常に砂嵐に見舞われる
As it stands, no matter how much land there is, the harvest it yields will always be meager.
これではどんなに土地があっても得られる実りは僅か
民が増えれば増えるほど　生産が消費に追いつかず困窮していく
The more our population grows,
production always falls short of demand, and we grow ever more impoverished.
It was always a fool's errand to live on that world.
あの惑星に住むのは　最初から無理があったのだ
But our second emperor, Emperor Gillzeria, was a believer in Aldnoah's power
しかし　二代目皇帝ギルゼリア陛下は　アルドノアの力を信奉し
工業力の発展ばかりに力を注がれた
and focused all his efforts on
developing our industrial capacity.
アルドノアを支配する王族の権力を絶対の物とし
The royal family, the masters of Aldnoah, ruled with an iron fist
民衆の苦しみには耳を傾けられなかった
and turned a deaf ear to the
pleas of our suffering people.
And then, the rising discontent of the populace was directed against Earth.
そして　民の募る不満の矛先を地球へと向けられた
ヴァースに対し主権を主張し　独立を阻み
He whipped the people of Vers into a frenzy, saying that it was Earth,
遠く離れた星から統治しようとした地球こそが　我らの敵であり
with their claims of sovereignty, obstruction of independence,
and attempts to rule us from their distant world,
苦難の源であると　ヴァースの民を扇動されたのだ
that was their enemy and the source of their suffering.
Horrifyingly, those lies were supported by all.
恐ろしい事に　その妄言は皆に支持された
They were the superior race,
自らこそが優秀な民族であり
豊かさを握っている劣等民族こそが悪であると
and the filthy subhumans who hoarded
Earth's bounty for themselves were evil.
Planning to invade Earth,
我らは地球侵攻を企て
we passed through the Hyper Gate and gathered our forces.
ハイパーゲートを経由し　月に戦力を結集した
Foolishly thinking all the while that our actions were just.
愚かにも　それを正義と信じて
And then, my Dioscuria, with its superior flight capabilities,
そして先鋒として　飛行能力に長けた我がディオスクリアと
and Orlane's Deucalion went down to Tanegashima as an advance party.
オルレインのデューカリオンが　種子島に降下した
How unimpressive...
何と貧弱な　これでは覚悟を決めて降下した甲斐がございません
This was hardly worth steeling our resolve and coming down for.
Do you not agree, Milord Saazbaum?
そうは思いませんこと　ザーツバルム伯爵
ああ　肩透かしを食らったな　オルレイン
Indeed. This is quite a disappointment, Orlane.
We will be able to take this planet far more easily than we expected.
この惑星　思ったより容易く手にする事が出来ましょう
Our people will be most pleased, to say nothing of His Majesty.
皇帝陛下は元より　我らが民も喜ぶ事だろう
何事
What's going on?!
Powerful space-time distortion waves?
強力な時空歪曲波
よもや　ハイパーゲート…
The Hyper Gate!
月が　割れた
The Moon... has shattered?
離脱するぞ　オルレイン
We're withdrawing, Orlane!
What's the matter? Withdraw at once! The surface is unsafe!
どうした　早く離脱せよ　地上は危険だ
時空の歪みが　反重力デバイスに影響を　飛べません
The distortions are affecting my antigravity device!
I can't fly!
今助ける
I'm coming to assist!
なりません　もはや手遅れ
You mustn't! It is too late! Leave me!
私に構わず　お早く
Hurry!
Orlane!
オルレイン…
;_;7
我は必ずや　オルレインの無念を晴らす
I will have my revenge for Orlane, mark my words.
伯爵　ザーツバルム伯爵
Count!
Count Saazbaum!
This is the battleship Deucalion.
こちら　戦艦デューカリオン
本部　入港許可願います
HQ, requesting docking clearance.
Welcome, Deucalion. Clearance granted.
ようこそデューカリオン
入港を許可します　6番ドックに着艦してください
Set down in Dock #6.
デューカリオン　了解
Deucalion, acknowledged.
I see it with my own two eyes, and I still can't believe it.
この目で見ても　まだ信じられないな
A flying battleship? Just like in my Chinese cartoons.
空飛ぶ戦艦　まるで日本のコミックブックだな
アルドノアドライブを起動出来ず　放棄したと聞いていたが
I heard it was abandoned because they couldn't activate its Aldnoah.
アセイラム姫を保護したというのは　本当だったのか
Those reports that they're harboring Princess Asseylum must be true.
We finally made it...
やっと着いたんですね
Yeah.
ああ
United Earth Headquarters...
地球連合本部
Commie Enterprises
Touchdown in 3... 2... 1...
着底まで　あと　3　2　1
着底　係留します
Ship is down. Now mooring.
I suppose this means our voyage is over, too.
これで　我々の旅も終わりですね
ええ　一先ずは
Yes, for now.
For now, ma'am?
一先ず
もし　このまま船を預かる事になれば　敵は…
If we keep the ship, what will the enemy do?
Now that we're here, we're safe, right?
ここまで来れば　もう安心ですね
This is a secret base 600 meters underground that was designed to withstand a nuclear strike.
核攻撃にも耐えられる　地下600メートルの秘密基地
大型シェルターには　たくさんの避難民が収容されてるそうですよ
They say that lots of refugees are being housed in the massive shelters here.
食糧も定員三年分の備蓄があるそうです
At capacity, they're supposed to have three years' worth of supplies stockpiled.
But apparently, the numbers don't add up.
ただ　数が合わないんですって
Are they over capacity?
定員を　超えてしまったんですか
その逆だそうです　備蓄の方が余ってるって
The opposite, apparently.
They have too many provisions.
It looks like most of the refugees never made it here.
避難民の多くは　ここまで辿り着かなかったそうです
If this place is destroyed, Terrans might go extinct.
ここをやられたら　地球人は絶滅かも知れないですね
>
It's huge!
でっか
Hey, Inaho.
なあ　伊奈帆　一応見てきたけどさ
>
(・‿・)
KIDDIK
I looked around.
There's lots of Areions sitting around,
so why would you keep using that Sleipnir?
アレイオンがごろごろしてるのに
無理してスレイプニール使わなくてもいいんじゃねえ
I'm used to it.
慣れてるから
That's all?
そんだけ
今まで戦った相手　装甲が厚くても　役に立たないし
Heavier armor wouldn't have helped against anything we've fought so far.
If you're okay with it, suit yourself.
伊奈帆がいいならいいけどさ
もういいんじゃない
Do we even have to fight now?
We can let the professionals do their job.
後はプロの兵隊さんに任せて　ねえ
Right?
Yeah.
念には念を　だよ
You can't be too careful.
It's got conformal power assist, huh?
コンフォーマルパワーアシストねえ
Aldnoah...
アルドノア
This is what started it all.
これが全ての始まり
Thank you very much, Inaho.
ありがとうございます　伊奈帆さん
私の命を助けてくださったそうですね
I'm given to understand that it's you whom I owe my life to.
No, it's because we're in a war.
いえ　戦争ですから
How many times does this make it?
伊奈帆さんに助けていただいたのは　これで何度目でしょう
I'm not sure. And I wouldn't say that I've saved it.
さあ　助けたつもりは無いですし
This is a war, after all.
戦争ですから
You're a kind person, aren't you?
良い人ですね
良い人です
You are.
After all this is over...
これからも…　これからも友達で居てくれますか
We will remain friends after all this is over, won't we?
Yes.
はい
良かった
I'm glad.
Milady, it's time.
姫様　そろそろお時間です
Very well.
はい　では行きましょう　エデルリッゾ
Then let's be off, Eddelrittuo.
If you'll excuse us.
それでは
私は　アセイラム・ヴァース・アリューシア
I am Asseylum Vers Allusia.
I am the Princess Royal,
ヴァース帝国皇帝レイレガリア・ヴァース・レイヴァースの孫娘　第一皇女です
granddaughter of Rayregalia Vers Rayvers, Emperor of Vers.
I address the people of Father Vers.
祖国ヴァースに告げます　この無意味な戦争の即時停戦を求めます
I call for an immediate cessation of hostilities in this meaningless war.
I am safe. Alive and well.
私は無事　生きています
It is not Terrans who made an attempt on my life.
私の命を狙ったのは　地球人ではありません
It was a plot by the Orbital Knights, who have their sights set on an invasion of Earth.
地球侵略を目論む軌道騎士の策略です
The Terrans are innocent.
地球人に罪はありません
Stop the fighting immediately.
今すぐ戦争を止めてください　そして　地球と和平を結んでください
And then make peace with Earth.
I beg you, put a stop to this tragedy.
どうか　この不幸に終止符を
これは…　タルシス
This is the Tharsis!
I retrieved it from Castle Cruhteo.
クルーテオ城から持ち帰った
あやつには過ぎた機体だ
He was unworthy of it.
Its Aldnoah drive is powered down...
アルドノアドライブが停止している　という事は…
やはり　クルーテオ伯爵は…
Which means that Count Cruhteo truly is...
Princess Asseylum's location
月面基地へのレーザー通信で
has been pinpointed via laser transmission to the Moon base.
アセイラム姫殿下の所在が特定された
The Moon base is under the control of those who feel as I do.
月面基地は我が同士の管理下にある
Her Highness' proclamation will reach no one's ears.
姫殿下の声明は誰にも届く事は無い
The final battle is about to take place at the enemy's main stronghold.
これより　敵本拠地にて決戦となる
Even with the full might of a Landing Castle, it will be no easy feat.
揚陸城の戦力を以ってしても無事では済むまい
My debt to your father is paid.
父君への義理は果たしたな
我が軍に付くも良し　地球に逃げるも良し
You may join my forces or you may flee to Earth.
好きにせよ
Do as you wish.
Milord Saazbaum, all launch
preparations are now complete.
ザーツバルム様　発進準備　全て整いました
Begin Landing Castle descent!
揚陸城降下開始
目標　ロシア　ノヴォスタリスク地球連合本部
Destination: UE Headquarters! Novostal'sk, Russia!
本字幕由诸神字幕组(kamigami.org)制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:つっちー   翻译:mam&低音子   校对:小可&zwx   时间轴:框子   压制:河蟹
Pidgeon-holing
決めつけばかり　自惚れを着た
Endless hubris
チープなhokoriで　音荒げても
The rage of my low-born pride serves no purpose
棚に隠した　哀れな　恥に濡れた鏡の中
On the shelves I hid the mirror
that shows the shame and misery of my existence
All others see in me is a burden
都合の傷だけひけらかして
手軽な強さで勝取るの術を
I try to hone myself to be victorious despite my mediocrity,
どれだけ磨いでも気はやつれる
but all it does is wear me out
ふらついた思想通りだ
It's a vision of utter foolishness
愛-same-CRIER　愛撫-save-LIAR
We all cry for love
Love saves the liar
愛-same-CRIER　愛撫-save-LIAR
Eid-聖-Rising HELL
I speak my vows and gaze at hell
愛してる　Game世界のDay
I love you, a day in a game world
Don't-生-War　Lie-兵士-War-World
Don't ask for war
Soldiers all lie in war
Eyes-Hate-War
In truth they hate it
A-Z Looser-Krankheit-Was IS das
A-Z loser's sickness: what is that?
Leben, was ist das?
Life, what is it?
Can you see that signal?
Signal, Siehst du das?
Rede, die du nicht weisst
Guess the things you do not know of your own volition
Aus eigenem Willen
Leben, was ist das?
Life, what is it?
Can you see that signal?
Signal, Siehst du das?
Guess the things you do not know
Rede, die du nicht weisst
Look with your own eyes
Sieh mit deinen Augen